<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>pfSense on Victor on Software</title><link>https://victoronsoftware.com/tags/pfsense/</link><description>Recent content in pfSense on Victor on Software</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoronsoftware.com/tags/pfsense/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Setting up a virtual router</title><link>https://victoronsoftware.com/posts/setting-up-a-virtual-router/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://victoronsoftware.com/posts/setting-up-a-virtual-router/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://victoronsoftware.com/posts/setting-up-a-virtual-router/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Setting up a virtual router" />&lt;div class="video-wrapper">
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uj_lB__QDTc"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
>
&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Traditionally, network routers used dedicated bare metal machines. However, in the last several
years, we’ve seen a rise in software-based routers that can be deployed either on bare metal, on a
VM, or even on a container. This means these virtual routers can be used to replace existing router
software on an older router. They can run in the cloud. Or they can be installed on do-it-yourself
(DIY) hardware. A couple popular open source software-based routers
are &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.pfsense.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>pfSense&lt;/a> and &lt;a class="link" href="https://opnsense.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>OPNsense&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-use-a-virtual-router">&lt;a href="#why-use-a-virtual-router" class="header-anchor">&lt;/a>Why use a virtual router?
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>For one, these routers offer enterprise-level features such as build-in VPN support, traffic
analysis, and extensive diagnostics, among others. Another reason is that having a virtual router
gives you the ability to experiment &amp;ndash; you can install multiple routers on top of your hypervisor,
and try all of them out. A third reason is that the virtual router may be only one of many VMs that
you run on your hardware. You can use the same piece of hardware to run a router, an ad-blocking
service, a media server, and other applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="advanced-virtual-router-installation-and-set-up">&lt;a href="#advanced-virtual-router-installation-and-set-up" class="header-anchor">&lt;/a>Advanced virtual router installation and set up
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>When setting up our virtual router, we chose to
use &lt;a class="link" href="https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/PCI%28e%29_Passthrough" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>PCI Passthrough&lt;/a> to allow the virtual router
direct access to the NIC hardware. Direct access to hardware improves the latency of our internet
traffic. In addition, we wanted our hypervisor to sit behind the router, and not be exposed to the
public. This reduces the attack surface for potential bad agents. However, routing hypervisor
traffic through the router made our setup a bit tricker. It is like the chicken or the egg
dilemma &amp;ndash; how do you put your hypervisor behind the router when the hypervisor is responsible for
managing the router? Below is the approach we used when installing pfSense on top
of &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.proxmox.com/en/proxmox-virtual-environment/overview" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Proxmox Virtual
Environment (PVE)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the initial installation, we did not use PCI Passthrough and instead used a virtual network
bridge (&lt;strong>vmbr0&lt;/strong>). We configured the router VM to start on boot.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://victoronsoftware.com/posts/setting-up-a-virtual-router/Virtual-Router-1.jpg"
alt="Initial virtual router configuration">&lt;figcaption>
&lt;h4>Initial virtual router configuration&lt;/h4>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>This allowed us to continue controlling the virtual router through the PVE web GUI. We set up the
router and enabled access to it through the serial interface, which we used in the next step. Then,
we put the system into its final configuration.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://victoronsoftware.com/posts/setting-up-a-virtual-router/Virtual-Router-2.jpg"
alt="Final virtual router configuration">&lt;figcaption>
&lt;h4>Final virtual router configuration&lt;/h4>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>In order to finish configuring, we had to plug in a monitor and keyboard into our hardware. We
accessed the virtual router via the serial interface from the PVE command line:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>qm terminal &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">100&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>We updated the WAN interface to use &lt;strong>eth0&lt;/strong>. At this point, the LAN interface &lt;strong>eth1&lt;/strong> had access
to the internet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In addition, we added a second LAN interface for the network bridge (&lt;strong>vmbr0&lt;/strong>). We made sure
firewall configurations for both LAN interfaces were the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next, from the PVE command line, we updated the PVE IP and gateway to point at the router by
modifying the following files.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>/etc/network/interfaces
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>/etc/hosts
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>After rebooting PVE, we had access to the internet and to the PVE Web GUI from our new LAN.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="updating-router-software">&lt;a href="#updating-router-software" class="header-anchor">&lt;/a>Updating router software
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Using a virtual router with PCI Passthrough creates a unique challenge when doing software updates.
What if the new version doesn’t work? What if you lose all internet access.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can mitigate potential issues. First, we recommend always making a backup of the router VM when
upgrading. That way we can easily roll back the change. Switching to a backup, however, requires
keyboard and monitor access to your hardware, since it must be done via the PVE command line.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another way to safely upgrade is to spin up a second VM running updated router software. The second
VM can be either from a backup or brand new. This VM should use virtual network bridges for its
connections. Once it is properly configured, we can stop the first router VM and switch the port
connections to the second VM. This flow also requires accessing the router via the serial interface
to update the WAN/LAN interfaces.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>